hey everybody welcome back once again to
another episode of The Art of
Photography my name is Ted Forbes and
today we're going to talk about color
theory a little bit and I want to talk
about uh the deliberate use of composing
using color in photographs and I know
that might sound obvious to some people
it might sound weird to others uh but I
want to look at this today and we're
going to look at some images that work
really well I want to go over to
Pinterest and look at some stuff I've
collected and show you guys where that
is if you want to study further um and I
want to talk about color in photography
now I know this is a weird way to start
this but I want to start it by talking
about black and white and personally if
you guys are familiar with my work I
shoot a lot in black and white that's
just my taste it's you know what I like
to do and people will ask me from time
to time why do you only work in black
and white well I don't only work in
black and white just the majority of my
work is in that um but the answer you
know I had to think about it and and
it's this to me it's that when you know
and I think it's this way to a lot of
photographers for that matter but when
you work in black and white you're
removing all the color information to a
photograph and this goes for any kind of
monochrome situation so like a cyanotype
even or if you're even if you're toning
or staining you're removing
the RGB color data from the the scene
that you're shooting or your picture and
that removes it from reality one two
levels you know and so obviously you're
not dealing with it you're dealing with
this tonal scale that becomes part of
the composition the light there's more
emphasis on what the light is doing and
you know these are just reasons I
personally like black and white photos I
like to look at them I like to make them
myself um now I also like to work in
color somewhat um and for me because
that black and white is that you know
removing that dimension of what reality
is or what you see dayto day the most
successful color work and the guys that
I look up to that that shoot amazing
stuff there's always or there's
generally well I would say there's
always this deliberate attempt when it's
successful where that color is a
successful part in the composition it's
integral to making it work it's not
dependent on the color but the color
really works to bring it all together
and I think this can work in one of two
ways uh you could be outshooting uh kind
of street style improvisational type
photography and you know you might see a
solid color wall so you can kind of
limit the colors in it maybe it's a nice
contrast or a complimentary color to you
know what somebody might be wearing you
frame up and you're able to get the shot
and a lot of the great work we're going
to look at today is done that way um
there's also deliberately planning a
composition in a studio type situation
or location shoot where you have that
control and if you can learn to kind of
plan this color stuff into it I think
you're going to get much more successful
photographs it's hard to do we don't
always do it well but um you know that
conscious effort is really important so
I want to talk about color theory a
little bit today before we get you know
too much into it and then we're going to
go over to Pinterest and look at some
images I've collected I'll give you the
URL so you can you can check that out on
your own too so come on over and let's
have a look okay so we're going to talk
about color theory here for a second and
uh I'm going to use a website to
illustrate this and this is a wonderful
website I used to use this when I taught
my college course and uh it it it's
really cool students are very receptive
to it it's a very visual way of learning
all the concepts we're going to talk
talk about here this website is
maintained by Adobe and it's called
Adobe I presume it's pronounced color
but it's spelled k l r so Adobe color
and uh the URL on that is kle r.
adobe.com there's also an iPhone app um
is free to use you do not have to be a
member of the Creative Suite to do this
um however if you do sign in and I
believe the account on this is free you
can sync some stuff up between the app
and the website and you can save color
combinations and Etc but anyway I want
to talk about what we're looking at here
and what you see in the middle here is
just a basic color wheel now the way
Color Works is you know color comes from
a in in in terms of the light source um
you have colors of red green and blue or
RGB that's the the light spectrum of
colors so it's the RGB color spectrum
and that's how we see things you've
heard the term RGB because that's how
your monitor works that's how it's
calibrated that's how your digital
camera Works um and so we're working in
an RGB color space and if we look on
here we have a color wheel and you know
you see these primary colors when
becomes the most red or the most blue or
the most green and combinations of these
colors uh end up making secondary and
tertiary colors so for instance
everybody pretty much knows that if you
mix blue and red together you start to
get purple or lavenders you can see down
in here and what we have here are a
series of little you know switches you
can toggle here and if I click and drag
these they stay well for the most part
the we have an analogous um color
combination which basically means we
have our primary here which is red and
when I move these points on the sides
they're going to stay analogous in that
they're going to be the same distance
from that red so you can see when I move
this orange towards yellow you can see
the bottom one down here starts moving
towards blue and we come up with this
combination of five colors down here so
what we're looking at is an analogous
color scheme here and also note that if
I drag the middle one down this red look
what happens to the colors below I start
to wash them out and they become you
know less saturated much lighter and so
saturation and value are kind of two
different things but you know you can
have a softer red or a harder red
depending on you know what you're mixing
it with and this is how color all Blends
together and if I spin this wheel around
I start to see various color
combinations that are indeed what we're
calling analogous and this is how these
colors are related to one another so
that's what we're defining here so if I
change my color rule to something like
monochromatic you can see that they all
stay in various values of one color and
so we think you know I earlier referred
to monochromatic as black and white well
that's just shades of black to white and
right here we're looking at shades of
red or if I start to move this dial
around we're looking at shades of purple
or shades of blue I can go over to
yellow or green or somewhere in between
you can obviously adjust the saturation
as well and our scheme here is locked
into one that is indeed monochromatic is
what we're calling that because it just
deals with one color at a time so that's
another color scheme if we look at these
these are just various ways of grouping
colors um that have relationships to
each other so the Triad scheme is a
little bit different because we're
taking three colors
um that are pretty much at you know if
you divide the color spectrum by thirds
that's where they sit uh you can go
through and play with all these
complimentary colors are opposites on
the color wheel and so generally they
have a lot of contrast to the eye
between them so if I take this red over
here and we we'll look at this an
example in a minute its complimentary
color relationship is to Green on the
other side of the color wheel so that's
what complimentary means is these two
colors complement each other because
they are opposite on the color wheel and
you you can go in you can do compound
Shades or you can do custom combinations
as well but mainly these top ones all
but the custom category these are ways
of looking at colors in ways that they
relate to each other um doesn't
necessarily mean they're always pleasing
to the eye but they can be because
there's a continuity there's a
relationship and there's you know um
there's a definition of how these colors
relate to each other so that's how that
works so go check that out that's color.
adobe.com kle r. adobe.com you can
download the app and check it out
incidentally if you are a designer this
is a wonderful tool because it does give
you hexadecimal values RGB values Etc so
you can save color combinations that you
like that you might be working for for a
client or something like that but um and
for photography I think it it is
interesting too there also is a way in
here where you can upload photos and
Sample colors out of the photos which is
pretty interesting too but now what I
want to do is I want to switch over and
let's talk about relationships of colors
in photography in a way that's very
successful so I'm going to go over to my
Pinterest account here and one thing I
want to show you guys cuz I do refer to
the Pinterest account quite a bit cuz we
keep collections in here um I'm going to
go over to my boards so if you want to
follow me on Pinterest it's
Pinterest.com Ted Forbes that's TEF R
bees I'll put a link in the show notes
and Pinterest has a way of doing pens
which I'm clipping from the internet and
arranging them in what they call boards
which are collections Now by default the
way the boards work and we've used these
on the show before you've seen them uh
the newest boards are always at the
bottom of this list so we're going to
scroll to the bottom and I have one on
color theory that I'm going to look at
here and I have three photographers here
um there are way more than this but I
think these are some guys that are
particularly interesting to me in the
way they used color I'm going to take
these a little out of order here this is
a very famous image this is the red
ceiling from Green Greenwood Mississippi
um 1974 from the wonderful controversial
William Egleston not everyone loves
William eglon I understand um I have
kind of a LoveHate with him myself but
you know these days it's more love than
hate so I'm showing him and I think this
is an important photograph to show and
you have to remember at the time too
that egon's career was beginning color
photography was not considered fine art
at all and eglon comes around and does a
you know series of major exhibitions at
you know Museum of Modern Art New York
Etc and all of a sudden he's the
photographer kind of breaks in and all
of a sudden color becomes accepted um as
an artistic medium in contemporary
photography and his images are a little
rough and they're a little raw you much
in the same way somebody like Robert
Frank kind of is when you compare him to
Cartier brel for instance um if you
compare eglon to other contempories of
his it's rough it's raw it's weird it
doesn't always work there's a there's a
tension that comes with it anyway this
is a very famous image that was taken in
Mississippi of this red ceiling and you
know what makes this work and what makes
you remember it and what makes it stand
out um despite the odd poster on the
back with the um you know various
positions being explained but anyway
side note um is the fact that this is
very monochromatic um remember
monochromatic were shades of the same
color well what you're seeing here are
shades of red um some are dark some are
light that's what you know defines the
depth what you see the three three
dimensions of the room in and it works
on that scale of being monochromatic um
you know which is very interesting uh
eglon also in a more accessible way did
some other photos there's another one
that I've shown on the show before um
that I love these these two women
smoking at a diner and what makes this
successful and what makes it work is
because you can isolate this down to
colors that stand out now obviously a
lot of these guys were shooting I don't
know for sure but what this was shot on
but I assume it was Kodak Chrome which
had you know at that time technology was
trying to catch up in the film world and
kodor had a very specific look to it and
it's very beautiful and it's very
workable with these types of images and
you know the main colors that stand out
are the green and the red you know the
red on the menu you know these seat
cushions are green and then you have
some you know secondary colors the skin
tones the pink dress but really the ones
that catch your eye are the red and the
green and the red is also pretty much
echoed in the brick on the wall ball
back there and those are the things that
stand out so if you take a quick Glimpse
at this photo your eye catches those
really quickly and those are remember
what we called complimentary colors
because they are opposites on that color
wheel the red and the green and so this
is an interesting photograph there's a
little bit of tension uh it's an awkward
pose it's the back of this woman's head
it's kind of neat too um in a kind of a
nostalgic sense and anyway that's one of
the things that makes that photo work
very well um another guy that I've shown
on the show before that I can never get
enough of personally is the wonderful
saw leader by the way there is a
documentary that is I don't know if it's
out yet I think it is on Saul leader
I'll have to look that up and and
discuss it on the show as well but Saul
was an early colorist as well um he
wasn't discovered really until the 1990s
he was a professional photographer did a
lot of fashion magazine work most of
that was black and white at the time and
he shot these color photos just his
personal projects for his own Amusement
fun personal gratification practice
whatever you want to call it and they
were kind of discovered in boxes in the
9s of course all still live today and
they're amazing they're they're
mind-blowing um you know if you just
kind of take a quick glance at this
photo again you see these primary colors
that are standing out here uh they're
very hard primaries but uh you are
seeing them as that and so you have the
yellow and the the red that make up the
taxi and then you have this orange and
guess what if you mix red and yellow
you're going to get orange so um you
could call these analogous in terms of
color and you see this a lot um Saul's
work also and this is not color related
but has um an abstract quality to it
there's lots of Street Scenes inv
variable weather conditions there's
definitely a style and look to it and
abstraction plays into that quite a bit
usually there's something in the
foreground that's blurred out that you
don't know what it is but the important
part is we're given enough information
in this image to understand that it's a
taxi and the color is a very Dynamic
part of that it doesn't Define that it's
a taxi it just tells you red and yellow
um the shapes combined with those colors
are what you know end up giving you the
the the um the conception of the car so
anyway um wonderful stuff another great
saw leader here um again with you know
the soft colors in this case you have a
real hard primary red down here that
stands out red is very sensitive or your
eye is very sensitive to the color red
so you don't need a lot of it um it can
make a wonderful accent color at times
you have some you know faded yellows in
here and then almost a faded blue light
in the background this woman's dress is
blue this really works um it works
wonderfully um compositionally in terms
of its color and and mainly too and I
want to point this out is because
there's not a lot going on in these um a
lot of times photography is not what you
put in the photo it's what you leave out
of the photo and that's the hard part is
getting things out of the photo so this
composition is not one that is going to
be a really easy one just to go to a
cafe and take I mean this I'm sure Saul
was deliberate with this um he just had
that kind of an eye to him and you know
and caught this scene it's it's a
beautiful picture uh a couple others
here again you see a lot of the same use
in Sals photos of the Blues Reds and and
yellows and again we see that here
interestingly enough though is this pink
umbrella back here is a nice little
accent color so sometimes you know if
you're going to let another color come
in just just a little Glimpse or a blip
of it has a really nice wonderful effect
to it at times um but anyway wonderful
stuff I also like how the blue is really
not created by any specific object it's
just kind of the color of the light and
being that it's overcast and cloudy a
lot of that has to do with you know at
this time what kind of film you were
shooting on and today's terms would
probably equate more to what white
balance you were set at um can have
various effects and you know that if you
shoot on the wrong white balance you can
get two blue outside but you can also
control that and make it just a little
bit blue if it works for your
composition so anyway some things to
consider um and then lastly the most one
of the more famous ones and I love this
this abstract of you know somebody
working on the street writing something
on a notepad um but it's taken from
behind a fogged up window and you just
see this yellow shape in the background
not sure what it is it's probably a
delivery truck um but you know it's not
clearly defined as such anyway
absolutely beautiful stuff saw leader is
one of my favorites um I also want to
talk about one other photographer today
who I think is an outstanding colorist
uh there's some other things about his
work that make it beautiful as well but
this is Luigi giri um that's spelled g h
i r r i on the last name go look him up
he is a wonderful Italian photographer
he died oh a little while ago in the
early 90s 1992 or so but did some
wonderful stuff um this first image will
we look at he was a kind of known for
his use of of Krome and Polaroid both
but uh you know you see a lot in those
images um the very simple color study um
and this is very indicative of his style
um when you start trying to count how
many colors you're seeing here they're
bounced around in the composition but
there aren't very many um essentially
you're dealing with that um you know
this this the blue and the uh you know
these jars and then you have the J
position of this blue lid over here
which is kind of interesting this is
probably set up to be so and then this
blue ceramic uh vase if you will over
here you have kind of this darker red
which shares a little bit of hue with
the wood on the table and this yellow
here and then the rest is kind of you
know not so much defined as being color
um and and notice that the saturation
level that Luigi used on a lot of these
is just very very minimal um it just has
I don't like the word flat because that
implies negativity and I don't think
it's a negative thing at all but they
are flat colors and and they're
beautiful they're amazing um they don't
have a lot of vibrancy to them but
that's that's the draw you know um again
another another Gary piece this is a
beach and uh what's beautiful about this
too as I opened the link accidentally um
is the colors that you get out of this
are these turquoise colors of how you
know the area here where I guess you
would play some kind of game or
something this ramp is a turquoise color
which matches with the ocean which is
not far from the blue the colors on the
swing set here of the um of the metal
and then you know in contrast to those
this blue and red here
um has it just has a nice feel to it and
and it's a very wonderful composition
and the color is a big part of his style
um another thing that Luigi G did a lot
and I'm sorry this is not a huge version
of this I will try and link up to a
bigger one by the time you look at this
um this is an image I'll zoom in here um
and this is one thing that that Luigi
liked to play a lot with in composition
was kind of this false sense reality in
the context of reality and what this is
is it's a it's a photo of a ship and the
page is torn and so it looks like it's
creeping up behind a sand dune or
something at first glance and then you
realize that it's just on a piece of
corkboard or something and the image is
actually torn but it looks like creates
the illusion that there's this wave
coming down anyway he he played a lot
with that kind of
metaphorical um it's metaphor but at the
same time it's also just kind of a fun
play um of composition between reality
and non-reality this is another famous
image of his these people that are
looking at a poster I assume it's some
kind of three-dimensional map but it you
know has this feel of these people
looking off into uh mountain range and
of course the mountain range is not real
and again look at the subdued colors of
the clothing um and also the limited
color palette and I think that's
important in all these it's not a ton of
colors and they're shapes that are
predominantly colored that work together
mainly the jackets these people are
wearing uh with the green the light blue
the um you know these pastel like this
yellow and then the way that echoes in
the poster as well so again wonderful
stuff um another interesting shot I love
that the accent color in here is this
yellow of this woman and I'm presuming
she's not looking at a real cavernous
Lake here she's looking at a painting or
it's a uh um some kind of street art
that's been torn up or something but
anyway um so you have that kind of comic
play going on there but also the back of
this woman there's that beautiful accent
of yellow in her dress which which you
know pretty much compliments the blues
and greens that you see above her so
anyway you know and I think this was all
conscious um you know with all these
photographers and this is how you end up
getting stuff that's interesting and
this is how you end up getting stuff
that makes sense and it you know I think
all three of these guys Egleston uh Gary
and uh sa leader all three uh you know
their use of color is a big part of
their style and there's two things that
play into that it's the relationship
between those colors and the simplicity
so there's not a lot that you're looking
at so they stick out um they have a
relationship with one another and then
also the fact that uh you know in in
terms of intensity and saturation of
these values too I think played a a part
in the way these guys worked look like
you know with leader you see kind of
these saturated yellows that are very
deep against kind of these gloomy
backgrounds a lot of times with a lot of
blacks and you know other colors uh
whereas you know aglon has a very harsh
approach too but on the complete other
end of the spectrum you have Lu Gary Who
does these you know Wonderful pastel
colored um you know kind of quirky funny
sometimes scenes and I think he's a very
very underrated photographer um and if
you don't know his work I will link to
him so go to the show notes and check it
out okay so we've talked a lot about
color theory today we've looked at some
color photographs and you know like I
said earlier I think that when this is
it's most successful they you know color
becomes part of a composition and color
works with your imagery um and has an
effect within that and I think that and
this may sound obvious but it's amazing
how hard this is to learn you know I
think as we evolve as photographers as
we evolve as creative people as we
evolve as artists most of this is
learning how to see and I know that
that's you know something you hear a lot
of people say it's fairly obvious you
know you're learning how to see I have a
friend of mine that a little bit older
than I am this was back in the film days
before everybody had a digital camera
and uh you know he was he is a very
Mentor type personality and a very good
friend and he's one of those guys that
if everybody's sitting around shoot
hanging out and shooting the breeze or
whatever somebody has a camera and he'll
say Hey you know check it out and then
he's kind of teaching everybody
something and he's a very good
photographer um on top of that and I
remember we were sitting there and and
with actually it was somebody it was his
son that was sitting there and he was
showing him he said you know he looked
at me he says you know most of this is
like you know learning how to see and
it's amazing that most people who are
beginning or don't have much experience
with the camera generally pick it up
look through the viewfinder they're not
actually looking at anything point the
thing in the general direction and voila
let's hope something comes out and
really good photography is always a
deliberate attempt to try to control all
those elements and learn how to see
things learn how to not only look at
something but there's an interpretation
element of it like you know if I see uh
you know a man standing on a next to a
park bench is that a great photo no it's
an interesting subject and then your
mind what makes you good as a
photographer is trying to interpret okay
what would make a good photo maybe I
wait for him to do something maybe I ask
him to pose maybe I change the angle
maybe the light's not right and I want
to recreate this later any there's a
million things that go into that um so
anyway I think color is the same way and
it's you know when like I said when it's
most successful and when it's most
dramatic and when it sticks out the most
is when it's you know one there's an
element of Simplicity to it and two it's
deliberately planned and I think it's
just like everything else in composition
um you know there's something to be said
for minimalist approach to things to
narrowing things down to just a single
tract of focus and you know no pun
intended and you know getting the
Clutter out of the way and really
letting elements speak for themselves
and then arranging them in a manner
that's beautiful so
all of it is easier said than done I
struggle with this all the time myself
so anyway I hope you found some of this
useful today I really hope you found
some of it inspiring um I love showing
work by people that I look up to and
these are always fun episodes for me to
do so anyway that's it for today and
once again everybody thank you again for
watching the Arts of Photography and I
will see you next time